hey what's up guys my name is Jenna
welcome back to my safe possible series
today we're gonna be talking about what
it means to be safe in C++ and just in
general the whole debate about modern
C++ and safety because I feel like this
is an issue that has been circulating
for a really long time and I feel like
it's kind of the more complex C++ we
actually get to in on this channel with
all the various projects and this series
I feel like more and more people are
kind of a little bit confused about what
the correct way to write C++ is and like
just there's been so much debate on my
discord on reddit everywhere about just
in general like how to write C++ in the
modern day because there's all these
people of course who are saying that
modern C++ is all you should be using
you shouldn't be touching things like
pointers like roll pointers at all ever
you don't even have to teach that
because you just don't even worth
knowing because it's very bad but then
there's a flip side of things people say
but people saying smart point is a
terrible don't use them they like
performance overhead whatever like just
roll pointers be a man and use a roll
pointer that's for you all you need in
fact you know be a man and manage your
own memory is kind of a thing as well so
I just want to kind of talk a little bit
about what all of that means so that
people who are kind of new to C++ and in
general people on my channel have just a
bit of a greater awareness of what
things like that mean and where you
should be concerned and what the right
choice kind of is so we're just gonna
kind of talk today and I might write
some code released so show some concepts
but really this is just going to be a
little bit of a casual open discussion
please participate by leaving a comment
as well with your thoughts I really want
to know what this community that watches
my videos the watch my videos actually
thinks furthermore I do have a discord
the channel comes like this Court is the
link to that discord so it'll be
somewhere on the screen and in the
description below as well so definitely
check that out because that's a whole
like I think there's like over three and
a half thousand members on that discord
and we talked about C++ and graphics and
game ends
and everything all the time and lately
I've been kind of more active on that as
well so anyway what is what does it mean
to be safe in C++ so a safe programming
or the concept of kind of programming in
a way that does that hopefully reduces
things like crashes or memory leaks or
access violations is something that's
kind of the hue like the human race has
kind of been improving on as time goes
on so with kind of the introduction of C
what was 11 we started to I would say
move towards concepts such as smart
pointers in favor of rural pointers
primarily because of the whole issue of
having memory leaks as well as not
knowing what memory has actually been
allocated or free because really all
this can be summarized into a simple
problem I need to allocate memory on the
heap that is a huge operation in itself
if you guys haven't seen my heap as a
stack video check that out in the top
right corner because that's really
useful to know and actually other videos
that I recommend you watch before
watching this one is definitely the
wrong pointers video which has saved us
what what pointers in C++ and also the
smart pointers video because that's kind
of what we're gonna be talking about
today and specifically again today I
want to focus on pointers and memory
rather than like other things like
exceptions or you know the other type
types of safe kind of programming or
things like you know error checking
whatever we don't care about that but
today we're just gonna be talking about
pointers so when we started kind of
gravitating towards smart pointers and
all that it can really all be summed up
into the fact that I want to allocate
here memory right that in itself seems
to be such a complicated part of
programming that we've constructed all
of these kind of constructs and systems
and ways of dealing with that in a way
to automate it and hopefully reduce
human error and all of this can be tired
really into human error right smart
pointers and kind of automatic memory
management systems exist to make to make
programmers lives easier and not just
easier but more robust meaning that you
don't you know it's not about the fact
that you don't have to deal with certain
things anymore because they're automated
it's also when you forget to deal with
with certain things you are fine because
it's handled for you automatically
so the concept of memory allocation
itself is really simple right I want to
allocate my memory allocation of course
on am I am talking about heap allocation
I want to allocate a block of memory on
the heap right what happens in that case
is you get a pointer back if the
allocation is successful you get a valid
pointer back to the beginning of that
block of memory and it will exist until
you explicitly delete it that is the
whole concept of what I'm talking about
really and the problem comes from I
guess a few aspects there's the problem
of what happens if I forget to free my
memory that's an issue because that will
cause a memory leak which could be
completely harmless and you wouldn't
even notice or it could be catastrophic
and it could be the result of your
program crashing because you run out of
memory then there's also the problem of
ownership right so who owns the memory
that has been allocated if I if I have a
roll pointer just a pointer to that
block of memory and I start passing it
from function to function from class to
class who is responsible for managing
and as potentially cleaning up that
memory right that's the ownership
problem because if you start just having
a roll pointer around then what you know
you know there will be kind of
programming scenarios in which you have
function a that manages that function B
that manages it you're not sure which of
those functions is going to finish with
it last but you need both of those
functions to actually have access to
that pointer so how do you say that okay
at the end of those two functions
completing their job that's what I want
to Freight out memory that's not
possible
unless you can explicitly say I'm gonna
run function a I'm gonna run function B
and then at the end of that I'm gonna
have like a third function or something
that is guaranteed to run after those
two functions are finished and that is
what's gonna before my cleanup step and
that obviously massively complicates the
whole programming just just programming
really
and that's something that we definitely
want to avoid so that's another kind of
ownership issue but really there's just
forgetting about the allocating memory
which is kind of more of a simple
problem because the solution to that
really is just you know to be able ittle
bit more attentive when you're
programming which again isn't something
when I'm saying like that's not it
that's that's hard to say right oh just
be a better programmer you know that
what does that mean like that's so
arbitrary that's so you can't just say
okay well yeah I guess I should pay more
attention to my code when I'm
programming that's not a solution right
that's just I'm just saying that that's
something that would be a potential
hypothetical fake solution to the
problem is yes to be a better programmer
and then you would need to worry about
more like kind of more complicated
constructs in order to delete memory
that has been allocated by yourself
explicitly right but then there's also
the ownership problem which is I have a
bunch of different functions that
require access to the starter we're all
in the finished I want to clean up after
that data like I want to be able to
deallocate that data but I don't want to
have to explicitly build something that
like manages that ownership or transfers
ownership because that's just going to
massively complicate things and I'm
gonna have to kind of keep track of that
manually and I know that when another
programmer comes up with the team and
decides to write something else that
many place that memory they're gonna
probably screw things up okay so those
are kind of the two big issues and the
reason why we kind of want to automate
the deletion of memory but really when
we talk about safety and C++ and
specifically all this smart pointers
stuff we are specifically just
automating one simple line of code and
that is the deletion of memory the
freeing of memory that is the only thing
we're dealing with okay into it
primarily in two ways and again the
smart pointers video covers all of this
so this isn't really new information in
this series but it's just as we can go
on with this series and with this
channel we're gonna be actually building
applications so in building frameworks
saying building actual production code
soon so because of that I want to just
kind of be on the same page with all of
you about that automating that single
line of code is can be very important
okay and I firmly believe that yes in
2018 doesn't matter about in fact I
almost regret mentioning in 2018 because
it doesn't matter at any time right in
any kind of
realm it is good to automate a lot of
things in programming
all right specifically the kind of
freeing of memory because it seemed to
be such a fragile and pedantic kind of
operation that people just screw up all
the time right
so yes smart pointers are really good
you should 100% use smart pointers never
in my life would I say you know roll
pointers only that's stupid okay I think
I think everyone agrees our that's
stupid
not using the simple course standard
kind of libraries smart pointers you
know that's fine some people may choose
to write their own right whether that
just be a scope based pointer which is
the equivalent of like a CV unique
pointer or whether that be like a
reference counting system which is
basically the equivalent of an STD
shared pointer that's fine right and
then you can introduce concepts like
awake references that's also fine right
will wake pointers that's fine right you
can make your own constructs I have
nothing against that sometimes prefer to
do that both for kind of the ability to
customize them to their own needs or
maybe try and squeeze out specific
platform you know platform specific kind
of performance constraints and concerns
by writing their own system which they
have a hundred percent control of
totally fine right but if you choose to
go with a one hundred percent rule
pointers kind of strategy for yourself
whether you're building it's not that
you're a bad programmer it's just like
why write like why do I do that it
doesn't make any sense and the thing is
I I'm somewhat guilty of this as well
like if I'm running code really quickly
I'll probably just default to using
world pointers the biggest reason why I
do that is because in the scope of
things they are still for me personally
easier to write and easier to read
because there's no thought that goes
into them you just put a little star and
you're done right and then if I want to
I can choose to delete memory but it
probably doesn't even matter because
again I'm talking about the constant the
context of a simple sandbox application
which probably won't be more than 100
lines of code because I just want to
test out one little thing or whatever
right and of course then in that case
it's like well you know am I really
gonna start dealing with it smart
pointers like why that's gonna kind of
turn my code into such a heavyweight
burden right whereas if I just had
rawrr pointers it would just be kind of
cleaner easier to read and i don't care
i don't care if i never free my memory I
don't care about ownership right because
all I'm writing is a little app and
there are a lot of people who say well
yes but even in a little sandbox
application you should be using smart
pointers because people might see your
code and might learn from it and might
be able then might do that everywhere
but that's stupid I mean think about it
really right why on earth should I not
be able to write a rule pointer for a
little sandbox application like how like
pedantic and ridiculous do you have to
be to decide that I'm never going to
type out a roll pointer in my life like
that's I just don't understand why like
something a lot of people I have met in
real life are actually like that which
is a bit annoying to me and people some
people just completely freak out when
they see real point as well but ever
seen me write real pointers which to me
is very confusing because like hey man
it's not like I killed someone I just
you know I just decided to kind of
manage memory myself a little bit like
oh no like it's so kind of silly it
sounds so silly to me and maybe that's
just me being like not really taking
responsibility for the fact that I do
have like over 100,000 subscribers and
all the people who watch my videos and
learn from them and maybe I should be
more responsible and then you know it's
almost like you know if a child saves me
crossing the road on a red light you
know because I don't want to wait for
the light to turn green before I run
across the road like then a child sees
that like that's kind of a bad thing a
little bit of a bad influence on that
child even though
what I'm doing is fine right I know it's
fine because they're gonna cause and you
know I want to wait for the light to
turn because I really need to hurry up
but the child sees that and I'm a bad
influence on the child is it kind of
like that where I should be running
we're all pointers I shouldn't be
running role plays at all because some
people wish for my videos might get the
wrong impression and might not have the
full context of why I'm doing that
like that's certainly a please don't
restart my computer in the middle of
recording thank you because if this
video fails I will be very upset anyway
I've got a talk before Windows 10
restarts because I'm recording my audio
through the computer and anyway doesn't
matter the point is
I'm probably dragging this on and I just
really wanted to kind of talk about this
so that's what this video is but anyway
my point being that I think that people
should a little bit stop about the whole
roll point is very smart points thing in
the context of a real framework or real
application that will be used by people
and might be production code yes use
smart pointers it is a very very stupid
move to not do that both for
maintainability and kind of reliability
of code as well as really just just
being able to write code freely right
without having to worry about when will
my memory get frayed oh no I forgot to
delete oh no what happens if I start
passing this pointer around I'm gonna
lose ownership of it all of that is
solved with smart pointers mostly right
maybe threading issues and other kind of
things
my bizarre things of course shared
pointer is not thread safe and there are
a bunch of other constraints that come
with using smart points like oh my goat
the solution to memory in general but in
but of course just speaking typically
but the typical case is that they do
help you a lot
so yes you should use them and we will
definitely be using smart pointers as we
get into more serious code don't get me
wrong it's just that at the stage of
learning C++ I firmly believe that you
need to you need to know what a broad
pointer is you need to know how memory
actually works
why because smart pointers are just a
wrapper on top of a rule pointer that's
all they are there additional auxilary
code around a roll pointer in order to
automate things which essentially are
just deletion right and freeing of
memory that is why they exist and if you
don't know what a roll pointer is then
you're not you do you're not aware of
what's happening behind the scenes and
since I'm trying to teach all of you to
be good C++ program it's not just I'm
capable of writing C++ code but more
like I'm capable of writing real time
kind of performance critical production
C++ code you have to know how everything
works that's why I make videos on how to
compiler the linker work and that's why
I like going in-depth into my videos
because I'm trying to teach you guys how
to actually be good programmers in C++
and in order to do that you need to
and how things work so if a child
pointer scares you then there's an issue
here in what I'm trying to do and
obviously your goals aren't meeting my
goals for what I kind of want to teach
so that's something that I think as a
community we need to talk about a lot
more because yeah it just ends up kind
of you know people end up saying that
I'll you know I'm teaching or obviously
for class or whatever because I'm using
old kind of things but the fact of the
matter is in my opinion and this is just
my opinion there is no factual
information about you should never use
smart pointers or you should always use
smart pointers those are two opinions in
the real world what you use will matter
a lot on what you what it is you're
actually doing right this channel at the
end of the day is just my opinion and in
my strong opinion you need to know all
these old things you need to know how
simple sauce works and how old these
things work and say buzz-buzz
if you want to actually be a good
supercross programmer right that's it
that's my strong opinion if you don't
like that then you probably you know
there's plenty of other good save
response resources out there I by no
means I'm the only one or the best one
or anything like that
I'm just one of the many signals wealth
resources out there on the Internet
you can buy books you can do whatever
you want but that's just what I think
which is why on my channel that's what
I'm going to teach anyway I hope you
guys enjoy this video if you did you can
hit the like button the comments section
below is made for discussion so please
let me know what you think and about
your opinions about you know programming
kind of stable as well safely I guess
but also what things you want to kind of
like if you think I'm focusing on the
right things if you think if you think
I'm focusing on the wrong things and
your opinion about the whole smart
points role bonus thing I really want to
read and reply to hopefully much those
comments and this port is the other
really good place to check out kind of
further discussion on single cells in
general and also all of my videos and
all that stuff anyway I'm really excited
for what's coming in the future for this
channel cuz I mean I think it's been a
month since my last video and I've been
both kind of dealing with kind of a
bunch of stuff in my personal life as
well as
on the down-low kind of planning you
know the the next year or so really of
this channel so I'm really excited to to
get into that and I'm sure you guys just
all the cool stuff is fun so I'll see
you guys next time goodbye
[Music]